CURRICULUM VITAE



A dedicated, passionate and capable research fellow with three years of teaching experience to undergraduate students in the field of History. As of now, published as many as five research papers in different national as well as international journals of great repute. A regular contributor of papers in different national and international conferences and webinars in India and abroad. A confident presenter and teacher, able to explain complex information to audiences of all levels.

Name: Suhail Amin Mir

Father's Name: Mohd Amin Mir

Mother's Name: Shameema Bagum

Date of Birth: 02 March, 1990

Permanent Address:

Village: Herri Bala, P/o: Trehgam-193224

District: Kupwara, Tehsil: Trehgam

State: Jammu and Kashmir

Address for Correspondence:

Room No.41, Sir Sayed Hall North, Aligarh Muslim University

Aligarh, U.P.-202002

Present Position:

Assistant Professor on contractual at Govt. Degree College Bomai Sopore. (Deptt. of Higher Education, Govt. of Jammu and Kashmir) session 2021

Research Topic: ACCESSION, INTEGRATION, AND ASSIMILATION OF PRINCELY STATES INTO INDIAN UNION: THE PROCESS OF ACCESSION, LEGITIMACY, AND THE ROLE OF PATEL AND MENON.

(**Status:** PhD Awarded on 18-01-2021)

Email Id: sohailmir105@gmail.com

Areas of Interest/Specialisation:

Modern Indian history, Contemporary Indian history, with a focus on the themes of colonialism, nationalism and communalism, Modern south Asia, European expansion in south Asia, Partition of India and Indian Princely states.

Academic qualifications:

Examination	Year	Board/University	Division	%age	Subjects
				of	
				Marks	
High School	2005	JK Board	1 ST	57	English, Urdu, Social
					Science,
					Mathematics and
					Science.
Intermediate	2007	JK Board	3 RD	40.93	G.English,
					Education, Political
					Science, History and
					Computer Science.
B. A.	Feb.2011	University of	2^{nd}	51.16	G.English, Urdu,
(Bachelor of		Kashmir			Political Science and
Arts)					History.
M. A. (Master	2013	DAVV University	1 st	72.5	HISTORY
of Arts)		Indore			
M.Phil.	2014	DAVV University	1 st	82.44	HISTORY
(Master of		Indore			
philosophy)					

OTHER QUALIFICATIONS:

- I. One year diploma in computer applications under Alma Vocational Training Programme 2010.
- II. Participated in one week J&K Scouts and Guides Camp held at Uri District Baramulla from 07-08-2005 to 12-08-2005 under J&K Scouts and Guides State Headquarters (KD) Srinagar.

Work Experience

 Two years teaching experience at CAS Deptt. of History AMU-Aligarh from 2017-2019 2. Six months teaching experience at Department of history, Government degree college Bomai-Sopore, Department of Higher Education, Govt. of Jammu and Kashmir from June 2021 to December 2021.

PUBLICATIONS:

- 1. A paper entitled as, "Changing Pattern of Policies: British Relation with the state of Manipur" published in the *International Journal of Humanities and social science*, volume 5 issue 6-2018
- 2. A paper entitled as "Women, Islam, and Taliban in Afghanistan in Colonial Times: A Hill Station Located in the South East Asia", published in fifth South Asian History Conference Proceedings (page 381-390)
- 3. A paper entitled "Lord Curzon and the Princely States: Some significant Aspects of British Paramountcy" published in 39th Session of *South Indian History Congress Proceedings* Hyderabad (page 205-207)
- **4.** A paper entitled as "A Historical Review of Trade and Commerce of the Princely State of Travancore during Imperial Rule", published in the seventh *South Asian History Conference Proceedings* (page 447-454)
- **5.** A Paper entitled, "Sustainable Tourism: A Tool for the Economic Reconstruction of J&K" published in International Journal of Enhanced Research In Educational Development Vol. 8 Issue 6,dec.2020 (page 16-19)
- **6.** A Paper entitled "Snippets from the Political Biography of V.P. Menon: A Critical Appraisal" published in *KALA- The Journal of Indian Art History Congress*, Volume No. 27, No. 1 (1) 2020-2021, (Page 625-631)

Participation in Seminars / Symposia / Conferences / Workshops:

- 1. Presented a paper on "Women, Islam, and Taliban in Afghanistan" in fifth South Asian History Conference on Women in South Asia: History, Challenges, and Potentialities held on 10-12 November 2017 and organized by the Department of History, Punjabi University Patiala, Patiala Punjab, India.
- 2. Presented a paper on "The challenges of good Governance: Accountability of Governmental agencies and development in India" in international conference on Good Governance: initiatives, Challenges and prospects, held on 13th November, 2017 and organized by the Department of Public Administration Punjabi University Patiala, Patiala Punjab, India

- 3. Attended the 75th session of the Indian History Congress held on 28-30 December 2014 at Jawaharlal Nehru University, Delhi
- Attended a Seven Days National Workshop on Research Methodology from 21-27
 Feb, 2018, organized by Career and Counseling Cell, Aligarh Muslim University,
 Aligarh
- 5. Presented a paper on **Lord Curzon and the Princely States: Some significant Aspects of British Paramountcy** in 39th Session of South Indian History Congress held on 8th-10th February, 2019 at department of history, Osmania University, Hyderabad, Telangana state.
- 6. Presented a paper on British Imperial Policies towards Princely States: A Case
 Study of Bhopal State in the 79th session of the Indian History Congress held on 26th
 28th February 2019 at Barkatullah University Bhopal Madhya Pradesh.
- 7. Presented a paper on **Dissolution of Princely Order in India and the formation of Democratic India** at two days national seminar on "Towards A Just India: Challenges and Prospects" held on 03-04 September 2019 at department of Political science Aligarh Muslim University Aligarh sponsored by ICSSR.
- 8. Presented a paper on A Historical Review of Trade & Commerce of Princely State of Travancore During Imperial Rule In seventh South Asian History Conference on Trade, Trade Routes, and Travels in South Asia held on 22 -24 November 2019 and organized by the Department of History, Punjabi University Patiala -Punjab, India.
- 9. Attended UGC sponsored **twenty one Days National Workshop on Research Methodology** from 09 November to 30 November 2019, organised by Human Resource Development Centre (HRDC), Aligarh Muslim University, Aligarh
- 10. Presented a paper on "Integration of the Princely States in India: A Neglected Historiography" at National Conference on 'Indian History Writing Traditions, held on 1st and 2nd February 2020 at Indian International Centre, New Delhi by Centre for Study and Research (CSR) Hyderabad in collaboration with Council on Historical Research and Teaching (CHRT), New Delhi.
- 11. Participated in a State-Level Webinar on **100 years of JALLIANWALA BAGH MASSACRE** held on 07th July 2020, organized by the Department of History,
 Brahmananda Keshab Chandra College-Bonhooghly Kolkata-Affiliated to West
 Bengal State University.

- 12. Participated in the Webinar on "Geo-Hazard: A Prerequisite to Geo-Conservation" organized by the Department of Geography, St. John's College Agra on 02 June 2020
- 13. Attended the Online workshop on "Quality Research and Scholarly Publications using Scopus and Mendeley", organized by Faculty of Social Sciences, Aligarh Muslim University, Aligarh in collaboration with Elsevier on 19th May 2020.
- 14. Participated in the national Webinar on "**Impact of Covid-19 on west Asian Economy: Implications for India**" organized by the Department of West Asian and North African Studies, Aligarh Muslim University- Aligarh on 27th March 2021.
- 15. Attended the Online workshop on "Quality Research and Publication ethics", organized by Faculty of Social Sciences, Aligarh Muslim University, Aligarh on 11th April 2021.
- 16. Attended online international conference on "Global Digital Economy-Managing Challenges and opportunity Confirmation" organized jointly by Birla School of Management, Birla Global University, India and Ljubljana University, Solvenia on 15-16 April 2021.
- 17. Organised online guest lecture at Department of History, Govt. Degree College Bomai on the topic "Literary Contribution of Bhagat Singh in National Movement of India" delivered by Prof. Varsha Survey of DAVV Indore on 9th August 2021.
- 18. Organised a National Webinar at Department of History, Govt. Degree College Bomai on the topic "India's Struggle for Independence" on 14th August 2021 guest speaker Prof. M. Waseem Raja of CAS Deptt. of History, Aligarh Muslim University.
- 19. Attended online international Webinar on 'Research and Publication Ethics' organised by Bharat Digital Academy and Social Development Federation, Agra on 12 February 2022.
- 20. Participated in one-day National Webinar on 'Teaching ESL Writing Skills to Indian Undergraduate" organised by the Department of English, Malla Reddy University, Hyderabad on February 04, 2022.
- 21. Attended online Training workshop on **Ethics for Research Involving Human Participants** organised by Jamia-institutional Ethics Committee and Faculty of Dentistry, Jamia Millia Islamia University-Delhi on & 7th March 2022.

Languages Known: English, Urdu,	miliui,	ana n	xasnımırı.
---------------------------------	---------	-------	------------

Suhail Amin Mir